Ajay Kumar Dwivedi

A ajaydwivedi.com
Nagpur, Maharashtra, India

♀ github.com/imajaydwivedi
☐ linkedin.com/in/imajaydwivedi

⟨ (+91) 703-231-2749
 □ ajay.dwivedi2007@gmail.com

Professional Summary

Site Reliability Engineer with 14 years of experience, I optimize SQL Server and PostgreSQL databases while collaborating with tech teams to build infrastructure automations using DevOps CI/CD pipelines leveraging scripting tools like PowerShell, Python, Ansible, and GitHub Actions. My Strong problem-solving and communication skills, I lead & train developers and administrators to effectivly build monitoring and alerting system for organisation.

Skills

Databases: SQLServer, PostgreSQL, SQLite, RDS, Managed Instance, Aurora

Programming Languages: § SQL, ☑ PowerShell, ♣ Python, ☑ JavaScript, ⑤ HTML / ➡ CSS, ☑ Shell Scripting **Tools and Frameworks:** Git, Linux, Ansible, Flask, Django, GitHub Actions, VS Code, Grafana, Prometheus, KVM

Virtualization, Container, Podman, Docker, Ubuntu, RHEL, PowerShell DSC, Infrastructure as Code (IaC)

Cloud Platforms: AWS, Azure

High Availability & Disaster Recovery: Clustering, Availability Groups, Mirroring, Log Shipping, Replication, Disk

Stripping, RAID, Multi Subnet Setup

Languages: English (proficient), Hindi (native)

Certifications

Microsoft Certified Professional - Database Querying	Oct 2013
Microsoft Certified Professional - Database Administration	Dec 2013
BrentOzarUnlimited Mastering SQLServer	Nov 2022
SOI Skills Blackbelt Professional	lun 2023

Experience

Senior Site Reliability Engineer (DevOps) AngelOne

02 2022 - Present

- Saved 80 hours/week DBA effort with single click Github Action based PostgreSQL Cluster deployment using Ansible Playbook.
- Optimized 10x SQL Server performance with D.E.A.T.H Methodology.
- Saved 1400 hrs/year by automating Transparent Data Encryption (TDE).
- Reduced 80% alerts with query tuning by fixing problems like Ascending Key, Kitchen Sink design, un-even threading, distributed query plans, MSTVFs, etc.
- Reduced 90% incidents by building monitoring and alerting system using PowerShell & Python.
- Automated Patroni PostgreSQL Cluster Health PagerDuty and Slack Alerts using Github Actions Workflow.
- Automated Patroni PostgreSQL Cluster Installation and Configuration using Github Actions and Ansible.

Database Reliability Engineer

Arcesiun

05 2020 - 02 2022

- Resolved 100s of incidents by moving 38 TB AG databases with PowerShell.
- Automated/Upgraded 30 Critical SQLClusters/AGs in 12 hours avoiding week long downtime.
- Improved database relibility with automated ScriptOut of entire SQLServer Instances for Disaster Recovery.

Database Administrator

TiVo

02 2018 - 05 2020

- Saved 40+ hours by automating SQLServer deployment and configuration using PowerShell.
- Reduced 80% transactional replication issues with latency infra.
- Reduced 80% performance incidents by building Delta Index Defragmentation automation for replicated & HADR databases.

Senior SQL DBA

United Health Group

10 2016 - 02 2018

- Saved \$1 million/year via DB Space Capacity Automation.
- Improved 50% performance issues with reduced VLDBs maintenance time.

Technical Lead

Ericsson Global

06 2015 - 10 2016

- 3x Performance Improvement via advanced query optimization like Recursive CTE and Table Partitioning.
- Lead 18+ developers for best practices and guidelines.

SQL DBA Developer

TATA Consultancy Services

03 2011 - 06 2015

- Moved 250+ large tables with each having billions of records using SSIS in 45 hours.
- Built data warehouse ETL pipelines using Pentaho & Kettle for high volume Liquor Retail stores.
- Saved 20+ hours/week by Automating core DBA tasks using dynamic SQL.

Education

Ladeation		
Bachelor of Engineering in Electronics & Communication Engineering RustamJi Institue of Technology	07 2006 - 06 2010 Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh	
Awards and Honors		
Tech Titan , AngelOne for 10x Performance Optimization on Prod SQLServer. Sapphire , United Health Group for Innovation and automations.	2022 2017	
Projects		
SQLMonitor: Open source Enterprise grade SQLServer monitoring tool	01 2021 - Present	
Built using TSQL, PowerShell, Python, and Grafana. Supposed the manifesting TSQL, SQL Samuel and appropriate transfer to the samuel and		
 Successfully monitoring 500+ SQLServers across environments. Observability alerts to Slack, PagerDuty and Email 		
Inbuilt auto action to Clear & Resolve		

HadrSync: PowerShell module that synchronizes all objects across Replicas in Availability

Groups

O1 2021 - Present

• Ensures zero sync issues during failovers/Drs.

• Detects & synchronizes even delta changes like changes in passwords, definition etc.

Availability

Notice Period: 90 Days **Relocation:** Open to Relocation **Remote:** Open to remote opportunities

FINAL NOTE

I have problem-solving mindset and love designing efficient database systems and solving complex performance challenges in collaboration with various tech teams. I help organisations build robust, fully automated infrastructure with PowerShell, Python and Ansible.